I welcome to day four of our time together.
우리가 함께한 지 4일째예요
This is a very important day.
오늘은 중요한 날이에요
Today we're going to be looking at the rise of the transformer, the architecture that sits behind most
오늘 살펴볼 것은 변압기의 발전입니다 이 과정에서 작업하게 될 LMS 대부분
of the LMS that we'll be working on in this course.
뒤에 자리한 아키텍처죠
We're going to be talking about stuff like Copilots and agents, and most importantly, we're going
부조종사와 에이전트 같은 것에 대해 얘기할 겁니다 가장 중요한
to be dealing with some of the basic foundational ingredients behind LMS that we'll be working on tokens,
건 LMS의 기본 요소를 다룰 겁니다 토큰, 연락처, windows, 매개변수 API
contacts, windows, parameters, API costs.
비용에 대해 작업할 거예요
Now, for some of you, this will be stuff that you're already quite familiar with, but I hope to go
여러분 중 일부는 이미 익숙한 내용이지만 좀 더 깊이 들어가 통찰력을
a bit deeper and show you some more insight, so this will still be a useful use of your time.
보여드리고자 합니다 비트를 통해 시간을 유용하게 쓰실 거예요
So hang in there and if you're new to it, I hope to give you a really good foundation to this world.
그러니 조금만 더 버텨요 처음이라면 이 세계에 대한 좋은 기초가 되길 바라요
But first we have to reveal the winner of our leadership battle.
하지만 먼저 리더십 대결의 승자를 발표해야겠죠
Hopefully you remember that at the end of the last session, I left you with Alex versus Blake versus
기억하시길 바랍니다 지난 세션 마지막에 알렉스와
Charlie, GPT four zero, Claude three, Opus and Gemini and that they were battling together to vote
블레이크 대 찰리 GPT 40, 클로드 3, 오푸스 제미니가 대장을
for the leader of the pack.
뽑기 위해 싸우고 있었죠
You remember their.
기억하죠?
Their pithy pitches to each other.
서로 간결하게 말하죠
And now I will reveal the outcome.
이제 결과를 발표하죠
So the first vote came in from Alex from GPT.
GPT의 알렉스가 첫 번째 투표를 했어요
GPT made the vote for Blake to be leader.
GPT가 블레이크를 지도자로 뽑았어요
Next up, the next vote coming in was Blake voting.
다음은 블레이크의 투표가 있었어요
And Blake voted for Charlie for Gemini.
블레이크는 찰리를 제미니제로 뽑았고요
So Claude voted for Gemini.
클로드는 쌍둥이자리에 투표했어요
Blake voted for Charlie.
블레이크는 찰리를 찍었어요
And so it all comes down to Charlie's vote.
찰리의 표에 모든 게 달렸죠
Big drumroll.
드럼 소리요
Make your bets.
베팅하세요
Decide who you think is going to be the winner.
누가 우승할 것 같은지 결정하세요
This is the winner.
이게 우승이에요
Charlie voted for Blake, and therefore Claude.
찰리는 블레이크를 뽑았고 클로드도 뽑았죠
Three opus Blake was the winner of our thoroughly unscientific, but quite fun challenge, and I hope
비과학적이지만 재미있는 도전 과제의 우승자는 오퍼스 블레이크입니다 사진에서
that that is aligned with your expectations from those pictures.
보셨던 기대와 일치하면 좋겠네요
And you should try this yourself.
여러분도 해 보세요
This is as I say, I ran this a couple of months ago and I'm sure that the results will be different
말씀드린 대로 몇 달 전에 실행했는데 이제 결과가 달라질
now.
거예요
At least you get different different pictures for sure.
적어도 다른 사진을 얻을 수 있죠 Get it
So by all means give this a try yourself.
그러니 여러분도 한번 해 보세요
You can copy my prompt or try something a bit different and see what you come up with.
제 프롬프트를 복사하거나 다른 걸 시도해서 비트를 만들어 보세요
And in fact, I actually wrote a game based on this.
사실 이걸 토대로 게임을 만들었어요
If you go to my personal web page@edward.com, you'll see that I have a game there called Outsmart,
제 개인 웹페이지 @ed워드에서 확인하세요 아웃스마트라는 게임이 있는데요
which is where I picked the various models against each other to try and do something a little bit more
다양한 모델을 골라 비교해 양적인 효과를 내려고 했어요 비트를
quantitative when they have to decide how to steal coins from each other, and it gives you a really
훔칠 방법을 결정해야 할 때요 다양한 모델의 다양한 기능을 볼 수
fun way to see the different capabilities of the different models.
있는 재미있는 방법이죠
And maybe we'll look at that a bit later on.
비트는 나중에 보도록 하죠
I'll see.
두고 보죠
All right.
좋아요
Well, with that in mind, let's move on to the main material of today.
자, 그럼 오늘의 주제로 넘어가 보죠
We're going to talk about the unbelievable history of the last few years.
지난 몇 년간의 믿기 힘든 역사에 대해 얘기해 보죠
And I have to pinch myself from time to time to remind myself of everything that we've been through.
가끔 제 볼을 꼬집어야 해요 우리가 함께 겪은 모든 일을 떠올리려고요
In 2017, Google, some scientists from Google released a paper that was called Attention is All You
2017년에 구글의 몇몇 과학자들이 발표한 논문은 관심만 있으면 된다였고
Need, and you can take a look at it.
여러분이 볼 수 있었죠
And this was the paper in which the transformer architecture was invented.
이 종이를 토대로 변압기 구조가 탄생했죠
This new architecture, including these layers called self-attention layers.
이 새로운 구조는 자기 집중 계층을 포함해요
And the thing that's perhaps most remarkable about this paper when you read it, is that it's very clear
이 논문에서 가장 놀라운 점은 발명가들 자신은
that the inventors themselves did not realize what an extraordinary breakthrough they were making.
이 놀라운 발견을 전혀 몰랐다는 거예요
They sort of remark on it as something that seems to be a surprising discovery, but they clearly don't
놀라운 발견인 것처럼 언급했지만 그게 어떤 기회인지 전혀 모르고
realize the door that they are opening and how much progress is going to be made as a result of their
있었어요 그 발견으로 얼마나 많은 진전이 있을지도 몰랐고요
In fact, the next year was when GPT one was released also.
사실 이듬해에 GPT 1이 출시됐죠
But for those that were, uh, around at that time and had used Bert from Google.
하지만 그 당시 구글에서 버트를 사용했던 사람들은 달랐죠
And then came GPT 2 in 2019.
2019년 GPT 2가 시작됐죠
GPT 3 in 2020.
GPT 3을 달성할 수 있죠
But most of us got the shock when we saw the power in late 2022.
하지만 2022년 말의 위력을 보고 대부분 충격을 받았어요
Was it November or December when ChatGPT came out, came out?
챗GPT가 나온 게 11월인가 12월이었나요?
ChatGPT was essentially GPT three, but also used GPT three and a half, 3.5 and also used this technique
챗GPT는 GPT 3을 의미하지만 3.5나 3도 사용했어요 인간 피드백을 통해 배우는 RL
RL reinforcement learning from human feedback that made it so very powerful.
강화 기술을 사용했는데 아주 강력해졌죠
Then GPT four came out in 2023, and of course this year we've had GPT four.
2023년에 GPT 4가 출시됐고 올해에도 4가 출시됐죠
Oh, and we've now, as we've seen, had zero one preview and other things are on the way.
아, 그리고 지금 보셨듯이 01 프리뷰가 있고 다른 것들도 준비 중이에요
It was interesting to see how the world responded to this change.
이런 변화에 세계가 어떻게 반응하는지 보는 건 흥미로웠어요
Initially, ChatGPT was such a surprise to all of us, even practitioners in the field.
처음에는 챗GPT가 모두에게 충격이었어요 심지어 업계 종사자들도요
It was really astounding how accurately and with how much nuance it was able to answer questions.
정말 놀라웠어요 얼마나 정확하고 뉘앙스가 많은지 질문에 대한 답을 줄 수 있었죠
That was followed by something of a backlash.
그에 따른 반발이 있었어요
There was a lot of of healthy skepticism when people said, this is really akin to to a conjuring trick.
건전한 회의론이 많았어요 마술과 비슷하다는 사람들의 말에 말이죠
This is what we're seeing here is basically really good predictive text.
여기 보이는 건 기본적으로 아주 훌륭한 예측 텍스트예요
If you bring up your, your, your text messages and you and you press the button to predict the next
문자 메시지를 불러와서 다음 단어를 예측하는 버튼을 누르면
word, sometimes it does really, really well, almost by coincidence, just because it's matching patterns
정말 잘 나올 때도 있어요 거의 우연이죠 패턴을 통계적으로 일치하거든요
And that's all you're seeing here.
그게 다예요
And there was a famous paper that's known as the stochastic parrot paper, which talked about the fact
추계학적 앵무새 논문이라는 유명한 논문이 있어요 그 논문은
that what we're seeing here is nothing more than statistics, and that it sort of gives, makes the
우리가 여기서 보는 게 통계에 불과하다는 사실을 강조하죠 우리가
point that we are falsely interpreting this as the model, having some kind of an understanding which
이걸 모델로 잘못 해석하고 있지도 않은 이해를 하고 있다는 걸
doesn't really exist.
시사해요
And it highlights some of the challenges and even dangers associated with us coming to the to the wrong
이 책은 우리가 잘못된 결론을 내리는 데 따른 어려움과 위험을
conclusions about that.
보여 주죠
But really, based on the progress since then, the pendulum has swung back a bit now.
하지만 그 이후의 진전을 보면 비트는 약간 흔들렸어요
And I would say that where we are as practitioners at this point is explaining this in terms of emergent
이 시점에서 우리 의사들은 이를 초현실적 지능으로 설명하고
intelligence.
있어요
That's the expression we like to use, which is saying that really what's happening here is that whilst
우리가 즐겨 쓰는 표현입니다 여기서 일어나는 일은 통계적
it is true that what we're seeing is essentially just statistical prediction, all we're doing when
예측일 뿐입니다 LM을 실행할 때 우리가 하는 일은 단어 혹은 토큰을
we run an LM is we're providing it with some, some words or actually some tokens and saying, given
제공하는 것입니다 트레이닝 데이터와 모든 것을 통해 패턴을
all of the patterns you've seen in all of your training data and everything you've learned, what is
보았고 다음 토큰이 무엇인지 가장 유력한 것이 무엇인지를
the most likely next token, what is the most likely next token?
알려주는 것이죠
And then we'll feed that in and say, and now what's the most likely next token after that.
그런 다음 그걸 피드하고 그 다음에 가장 가능성이 큰 토큰이 뭔지 말하죠
And all it is doing is predicting this next token.
다음 토큰을 예측하는 게 전부죠
That is true.
맞아요
But nonetheless, as a byproduct of doing this at such massive scale with trillions of different weights
하지만 그렇다고 해도 거대한 규모로 작업하면서 모델 내부에서 수조 개의 다른 중량을 설정해
that are being set internally in the model to control how it will make that prediction.
예측을 어떻게 할지 통제하는 부산물이죠
A byproduct of this level of scale is that we see this effect that we call emergent intelligence, which
그 정도 수준의 부산물로 발생하는 효과가 있는데 우리는 이를 비상 지능이라고 부릅니다
is an apparent intelligence.
명백한 지능이죠
It is as if the model is really understanding what we're telling it.
모델이 우리가 말하는 걸 정말 이해하는 것 같아요
It is, of course, true that this is really something that is imitating understanding.
이해를 모방하는 것이라는 건 물론 사실이에요
It's just seeing the patterns and replicating them.
패턴을 보고 복제하는 거예요
But there is this emergent property that it apparently is able to show this level of intelligence that
하지만 이 신흥 속성이 우리가 매일 개척자 모델을 사용할 때 경험하는 수준의
we all experience when we use these frontier models every day.
지능을 보여줄 수 있다는 걸 보여주죠
All right.
좋아요
Hopefully that's given you food for thought.
잘 생각해 보세요
Interested to hear where you stand on this debate.
이번 토론에 대한 당신 입장이 궁금하군요
By all means post that or let me know.
post를 하시거나 저에게 알려주세요.
And in the next lecture we will talk more about some of the theory behind this.
다음 강의에서는 이 이론에 대해 더 자세히 이야기해 보죠
And also look at some of the discoveries that we've had along the way.
그 과정에서 발견한 것들도 살펴볼 거예요